Guide to the William Sloane Coffin, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence, 1940-1983; Series I
  - General
    - Terkel, Studs, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - Thomas, Norman, 1961-1968 (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - Turnage, William A., 1966-1975 (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - U, 1960-1971 (Box 8, Folder 191)
    - Unsworth, Richard P., 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 192)
    - V, 1960-1975 (Box 8, Folder 193)
    - W, 1956-1983 (Box 8, Folder 194 - 200)
    - Wagoner, Walter D., 1961-1967 (Box 8, Folder 201)
    - Walters, Robert E., 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 202)
    - Wofford, Harris, 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 203)
    - Wolff, Morris, 1963-1971 (Box 8, Folder 204)
    - Y, 1963-1970 (Box 8, Folder 205)
    - Z, 1967-1973 (Box 8, Folder 206)
    - Unidentified and first name only, 1946-1976 (Box 8, Folder 207 - 209)
  - Family
    - Bacon, Margaret [aunt], 1944-1969, undated (Box 9, Folder 210)
    - Coffin, Amy [daughter], 1963 (Box 9, Folder 211)
    - Coffin, Catherine [mother], 1944-1947, undated (Box 9, Folder 212 - 218)
    - Coffin, Dorothy [aunt], 1964-1969 (Box 9, Folder 219)
    - Coffin, Eva [wife; letters to WSC in Africa], 1960, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 220)
    - Coffin, Margot [sister], Circa 1945-1946 (Box 9, Folder 221)
    - Coffin, Ned [brother; includes letters written by Ned Coffin to Catherine Coffin], 1940-1950, 1962, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 222 - 224)
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence, 1971, undated (Box 9, Folder 225)
  - Public opinion mail
    - General
      - Con, 1964-1973 (Box 10, Folder 226 - 229)
      - Pro
        - 1963-1968 (Box 10, Folder 230 - 236)
        - 1973-1975 (Box 11, Folder 237 - 248)
    - "Appeal for Theological Affirmation" [statement released from Theological Affirmations Conference at Hartford], 1975 (Box 12, Folder 249 - 251)
    - Conspiracy trial
      - Con, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 252 - 253)
      - Pro, 1967-1969, undated (Box 12, Folder 254 - 265)
    - Freedom rides, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 266 - 269)
    - Glamour magazine article, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 270 - 273)
  - Speaking engagements
    - Accepts, 1959-1968, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 274 - 289)
    - Declines
      - 1964-1968 (Box 15, Folder 290 - 301)
      - 1969-1972 (Box 16, Folder 302 - 311)
- Subject Files, 1959-1987; Series II
  The series is arranged alphabetically by a mixture of corporate and topical headings largely derived from Coffin's own folder titles. It includes a wide range of documentation of the movements, organizations, and events in which Coffin participated. Files include correspondence, printed matter, clippings, ephemera and other materials collected and created by Coffin. Although the contents vary widely, a number of important themes are discernible in the series including relief work, race and civil rights, Vietnam protests, amnesty for draft resisters, and disarmament. Many of these themes are also evident in other parts of the collection, particularly Series I and Series IV.
  Most of the documentation of Coffin's efforts to organize and supply relief work to other countries can be found under Operation Crossroads Africa and Peace Corps. The Operation Crossroads Africa files contain correspondence with James Robinson and other Crossroads Africa officials and participants. Other papers that illustrate Coffin's commitment to relief work in Africa can be found in the Africa file and American Committee on Africa file. The Peace Corps material includes correspondence with Sargent Shriver, Spencer Summers, William Haddad, Joshua Miner, and Bill Moyers, among others, and documents Coffin's early influence on the program. Materials filed under Outward Bound document Coffin's connection with that program and his use of it as a model for training Peace Corps volunteers. The series also includes material relating to Coffin's work with the Commission on Youth Services Program and the National Service Program.
  The nine "Race relations" folders comprise the most substantive materials relating to Coffin's civil rights work and include documentation from a wide variety of groups and individuals. The files predominantly contain correspondence and collected materials that document Coffin's organizing efforts and views on race, as well as those of others.Organizations documented include the Congress On Racial Equality, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Legal Defense Fund, Northern Student Movement, and the Southern Christian Leadership Conference. Coffin also kept separate folders of materials relating to several of these groups and they are listed under their corporate names. Cross references have been provided. The series includes other materials relating to race and the civil rights movement under the following headings: Civil rights march on Washington, DC; Freedom rides; and United States Commission on Civil Rights, Connecticut Advisory Board.
  Coffin's anti-war efforts comprise another major part of this series, spread over many overlapping files. The most voluminous and substantive material can be found under the headings Clergy and Laity Concerned About Vietnam (CALCAV); Americans for Reappraisal of Far-Eastern Policy (AFRFEP); Draft resistance; Conscientious objectors; Resist: A Call to Resist Illegitimate Authority; and Vietnam Summer. Rather than representing the inner workings of the organization Coffin helped to found, the CALCAV files serve as more of a topical file of Coffin's anti-war activities. The AFRFEP materials document the work of an earlier group formed to examine and protest United States foreign policy in the Far East. The Draft resistance materials include correspondence, flyers, publications, and other documents of the work of Coffin and others to contest the conscription of young men into the military. These materials include some documentation of Coffin's indictment and trial on charges of conspiring to aid draft resisters. Other documentation relating to this case can be found under the William Sloane Coffin Jr. Defense Fund. A large portion of the Draft resistance papers also consists of letters written to Coffin from individual resisters. These letters document their decisions, efforts, and problems. Documentation under the heading Conscientious objectors includes correspondence of a similar nature, which chronicles Coffin's work to secure conscientious objector status for a variety of individuals. The "Resist" folders document Coffin's collaborative effort to produce the eloquent justification for the use of civil disobedience to protest the war. Vietnam Summer material provides a significant view of the workings and accomplishments of the group, through reports, project profiles, correspondence and memoranda, and posters. A large amount of collected materials, largely newspaper and magazine articles, that provide background information on the anti-war movement have been filed under the generic heading Vietnam. Other folders that contain documentation of protest movements against the Vietnam War can be found under American Friends Service Committee; Committee of Responsibility to Save War Burned and War Injured Vietnamese Children; Fellowship of Reconciliation; Midwest Committee for Draft Counseling; Mobilizations; National Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam; New Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam; Peace groups; and United States Study Team on Religious and Political Freedom in Vietnam.
  Related to his anti-Vietnam war work, the series also includes significant documentation of Coffin's involvement in the amnesty and disarmament movements. The Amnesty for draft resisters materials hold a variety of information on this movement, much of it collected by Coffin rather than created by him. With the end of the Vietnam War, Coffin's efforts progressed into the disarmament movement. His efforts in this area are documented under the following headings: International Hearing on Nuclear Weapons and Disarmament; and SANE (National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy). Papers documenting the Voter's Pledge Campaign comprise the bulk of the SANE materials, which do not contain records from his tenure as president of the organization. Researchers should consult the Audiovisual materials for access to nearly thirty audiocassette recordings of presentations made at the Waging War in the Nuclear Age Conference held in 1987 as part of the Riverside Church Disarmament Program.
  Several relatively minor themes can be discerned throughout the remainder of the series. In the course of his peace and disarmament work, Coffin collected papers relating to several southeast Asian and Latin American countries. These materials generally date from the late 1970s and 1980s and are listed under country names, as well as the following headings: Campaign for Civil Rights; Center for the Study of the Americas; Institute of Social Studies; National Appeal for Justice in Latin America; "Sanctuary and the Law: A Guide for Congregations;" and Solidarity Committee with the Argentine People. A substantial amount of documentation, dating from the 1970s, exists for the Institute for World Order. Coffin's involvement in campus ministry groups and other religious organizations can be found under the Fund for Theological Education (Rockefeller Foundation), National Association of College and University Chaplains, National Campus Ministry Association, National Council of Churches of Christ, and New Haven Council of Churches. Finally, the series includes material relating to local social and political groups based in New Haven, including the Black Panther Party, Black Women's Boycott, Community Progress, Inc., and New Haven Women's Liberation.
  - Abortion, 1976-1977 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - ACCION, 1962-1966 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Africa [correspondence,memoranda, and minutes from several students and student groups working on African relief], 1961-1970 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - American Committee on Africa, 1966-1970 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1963-1970 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Americans for Reappraisal of Far Eastern Policy
    - General, 1965-1966 (Box 17, Folder 6 - 7)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 17, Folder 8 - 10)
  - Amnesty for draft resisters movement
    - Articles and background information, 1969-1975 (Box 17, Folder 11 - 14)
    - American Civil Liberties Union Project on Amnesty, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Americans for Amnesty, Circa 1972-1973 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Inter-religious Conference on Amnesty, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Statements on amnesty, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Amnesty International, 1966, 1973, undated (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Andover Alumni Council, 1963-1965 (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Anti-ballistic missiles, 1968-1969 (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Bailey, Donnal [poetry], 1971, undated (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Benevolence requests [miscellaneous], 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - "The Black Manifesto" [by Religious News Service], Undated (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Black Panther Party, 1969, undated (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Black Women's Boycott [New Haven], 1968 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Cambodia [press releases by the Permanent Mission of Cambodia to the United States], 1970 (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Campaign for Civil Rights [United States Covert Actions Against Nicaragua: A Public Forum], 1982 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Center for the Right to Privacy, 1974-1975 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - Center of the Study of the Americas ["Honduras: Base for Intervention." Report of a fact finding trip.], 1984 (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - Chile, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - Church investments, 1970-1972 (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - Churches of the greater New Haven area, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - Citizens for Government Restraint, Inc., 1968 (Box 18, Folder 34)
  - Civil disobedience [miscellaneous writings of others], 1963-1973 (Box 18, Folder 35)
  - Civil rights march on Washington DC, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 36)
  - Clergy And Laity Concerned About Vietnam (CALCAV)
    - General, 1965-1974, undated (Box 19, Folder 37 - 46)
    - "Conscience and Conscription: A Statement by CALCAV", 1967 (Box 19, Folder 47)
    - Help Unsell the War Project, 1972, undated (Box 19, Folder 48)
    - Posters
      See: Oversize Folder 1
    - Publications, 1967-1973, undated (Box 19, Folder 49)
    - Steering Committee retreat, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 50)
    - "Why are the Clergy Concerned about Vietnam"
      See: Series IV. Writings, 1945-1984 Folder 122 - 123
  - Coalition for the Homeless, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 51)
  - Commission on Youth Service Projects, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 52)
  - Committee for "Alternatives to Violence", Circa 1969 (Box 19, Folder 53)
  - Committee of Responsibility to Save War Burned and War Injured Vietnamese Children, 1967, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 54)
  - Committee to Defend the Conspiracy [holiday card from the Chicago Seven], Circa 1968 (Box 19, Folder 55)
  - Common People's Party, 1970, undated (Box 19, Folder 56)
  - Communication Group on Conscription and Amnesty, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 57)
  - Community Progress, Inc., 1964-1965 (Box 19, Folder 58)
  - Concerned Citizens. "Human Beings Fused Together"
    See: Audiovisual Materials Box 64
  - Congress On Racial Equality
    See: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 169 - 177
  - Congressional Action Fund, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 59)
  - Connecticut Conference on the United Church of Christ, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 60)
  - Connecticut Police and Community Relations, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 61)
  - Conscientious Objectors, 1967-1972 (Box 20, Folder 62 - 63)
  - Corporate responsibility, 1971-1973 (Box 20, Folder 64 - 66)
  - Council on Religion and International Affairs, 1972-1973, undated (Box 20, Folder 67)
  - Danforth Foundation
    - General, 1959-1964, undated (Box 20, Folder 68)
    - Study of Campus Ministry, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 69)
  - Deerfield, Illinois housing discrimination case, 1961, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 70)
  - Disarming God's World: Presbytery of New York City, Circa 1977-1978 (Box 20, Folder 71)
  - Draft resistance, 1967-1971, undated (Box 20, Folder 72 - 79)
  - Drugs, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 80)
  - East Harlem Protestant Parish, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 81)
  - Ecumenical Institute [Jerusalem], 1984-1985 (Box 21, Folder 82)
  - El Salvador, 1980-1983 (Box 21, Folder 83)
  - Emergency Committee for a National Mobilization Against Racism, Undated (Box 21, Folder 84)
  - Emmaus [ecumenical community and center in New York City], 1971, undated (Box 21, Folder 85)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1965-1970 (Box 21, Folder 86)
  - Freedom and Peace Party [leaflet supporting Dick Gregory for President], 1968 (Box 21, Folder 87)
  - Freedom rides
    - Articles and pamphlets, 1960-1961 (Box 21, Folder 88)
    - Public opinion mail
      See: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 169 - 177 See: Series I. Correspondence, 1940-1983 Folder 266 - 269
  - Friends of Danilo Dolci, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 89)
  - Fund for Theological Education [Rockefeller Foundation], 1959-1974, undated (Box 21, Folder 90 - 93)
  - Ginsberg, Allen [letter to Secretary of Treasury outlining reasons for tax resistance], 1969 (Box 21, Folder 94)
  - Greater Boston Walk for Hunger, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 95)
  - Harrisburg Eight [pamphlet by Edward LeRoy Long, Jr.], 1971 (Box 21, Folder 96)
  - Hertzburg, Arthur. "Jewish and Christian Identity in the Secular World" [talk]
    See: Audiovisual Materials Box 65
  - "The Homosexual and the Church" [panel discussion with Bill Johnson, Susan Day, Henri Nouwen, and Jim Dittes]
    See: Audiovisual Materials Box 67
  - Institute on the Church and International Responsibility, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 97)
  - Institute for World Order
    - General, 1972-1973 (Box 21, Folder 98)
    - Arms race, 1977 (Box 21, Folder 99)
    - National University Conference on Hunger, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 100)
    - Seminar on World Order Value Problems, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 101 - 103)
    - World Military and Social Expenditures [reports], 1974, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 104)
  - Institute of Social Studies. "An Alternative Policy for Central America and the Carribean" [summary and conclusions from policy workshop], 1983 (Box 22, Folder 105)
  - Interfaith Consultation for Peace in the Middle East, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 106 - 107)
  - International Hearing on Nuclear Weapons and Disarmament [Amsterdam], 1981 (Box 22, Folder 108)
  - Robert F. Kennedy Memorial, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 109)
  - The Liberation School, 1970 (Box 22, Folder 110)
  - Male chauvinism, 1970, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 111)
  - March 4 movement, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 112)
  - Marriage ceremonies, Undated (Box 22, Folder 113)
  - Martin Luther King Jr. Memorial Center, 1968-1971, undated (Box 22, Folder 114)
  - Middle East [documents re: Israel and Palestine used as background information for a trip to Israel], 1985, undated (Box 22, Folder 115)
  - Midwest Committee for Draft Counseling, 1969 (Box 22, Folder 116)
  - Mobilizations, 1965-1969 (Box 22, Folder 117)
  - National Appeal for Peace with Justice in Central America, 1983, undated (Box 23, Folder 118)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
    - General, 1965-1972 (Box 23, Folder 119)
    - Legal Defense Fund, 1966-1971 (Box 23, Folder 120)
  - National Association of College and University Chaplains, 1960-1976 (Box 23, Folder 121 - 125)
  - National Association of Independent Schools, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 126)
  - National Campus Ministry Association, 1964 (Box 23, Folder 127)
  - National Conference for New Politics, 1966-1967 (Box 23, Folder 128 - 130)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ, 1962-1970 (Box 23, Folder 131)
  - National Interest Fund, 1962 (Box 23, Folder 132)
  - National Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 133)
  - National Service Program, 1965-1969, undated (Box 23, Folder 134 - 137)
  - Negotiation Now Campaign, 1967 (Box 23, Folder 138)
  - New Haven Council of Churches, 1962-1964 (Box 23, Folder 139 - 140)
  - New Haven Women's Liberation, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 141)
  - New International Economic Order, 1976 (Box 24, Folder 142)
  - New Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam, 1970, undated (Box 24, Folder 143)
  - New World Foundation Meeting on Entrepreneur Conference [includes remarks by Ned Coffin and Harriet Coffin], 1976 (Box 24, Folder 144)
  - Nixon, Richard M. [petition for impeachment], Undated (Box 24, Folder 145)
  - Northern Student Movement, 1962-1963 (Box 24, Folder 146)
    See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1959-1987 Folder 169 - 177
  - Operation Crossroads Africa
    - General, 1959-1966, undated (Box 24, Folder 147 - 154)
    - CBS News documentary "Crossroads Africa: Pilot for a Peace Corps"
      See: Audiovisual Materials Box 46U
  - Outward Bound, 1962-1970 (Box 25, Folder 155 - 156)
  - Palme, Olof [memorial service], 1986 (Box 25, Folder 157)
  - Peace Corps, 1961-1966, undated (Box 25, Folder 158 - 163)
  - Peace groups [miscellaneous], 1970-1971 (Box 25, Folder 164)
  - People's Bicentennial Commission, 1974-1976 (Box 25, Folder 165)
  - People's Peace Treaty, 1971 (Box 25, Folder 166)
  - The Philippines, 1976 (Box 25, Folder 167)
  - The Press [telephone number sheet], undated (Box 25, Folder 168)
  - Race relations, 1961-1968 (Box 26, Folder 169 - 177)
  - Ramparts, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 178)
  - Redress, 1972 (Box 26, Folder 179)
  - Rehnquist, William, 1971 (Box 26, Folder 180)
  - Resist: A Call to Resist Illegitimate Authority, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 181 - 183)
  - The Ripon Society, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 184)
  - Riverside Church Disarmament Program [see Audiovisual materials for recordings of presentations made at the 1987 "Waging War in the Nuclear Age" Conference], 1980-1981 (Box 26, Folder 185)
  - Robinson, David et. al. vs. State of Florida, 1964 (Box 26, Folder 186)
  - Romanyuk, Vasyl, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 187)
  - Rostow, Eugene V. ["Chief Justice Earl Warren and the Gift for Action," remarks at American Trial Lawyers Association Luncheon honoring Earl Warren], 1968 (Box 26, Folder 188)
  - St. Augustine, Florida civil rights project, 1964-1965 (Box 27, Folder 189)
  - "Sanctuary and the Law: A Guide for Congregations", 1984 (Box 27, Folder 190)
  - SANE (National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy)
    - General, 1966, 1969 (Box 27, Folder 191)
    - Voter's Pledge Campaign, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 192)
  - Sierra Leone project, Undated (Box 27, Folder 193)
  - Solidarity Committee with the Argentine People, 1976-1977, undated (Box 27, Folder 194)
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference
  - Southern Poverty Law Center
    - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 27, Folder 195 - 201)
    - Dees, Morris, 1974-1975 (Box 27, Folder 202)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1975 (Box 27, Folder 203)
  - Stockholm Conference on Vietnam, 1969 (Box 27, Folder 204)
  - Student Christian Movement in New England, 1965-1966 (Box 27, Folder 205 - 209)
  - Student Communications Network, Circa 1968 (Box 27, Folder 210)
  - Surtax [proposed ten percent tax to finance the Vietnam War], 1967 (Box 27, Folder 211)
  - Television program proposal, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 212)
  - Terkel, Studs, Undated (Box 28, Folder 213)
  - Tri-Continental Information Center, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 214)
  - "The Undeveloped Half of Civilization", Undated (Box 28, Folder 215)
  - United Church of Christ, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 216)
  - United Nations International Relief Task Force, Circa 1969 (Box 28, Folder 217)
  - United States Commission on Civil Rights. Connecticut Advisory Board, 1964-1970 (Box 28, Folder 218 - 221)
  - United States Servicemen's Fund, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 222)
  - United States Study Team on Religious and Political Freedom in Vietnam, 1969 (Box 28, Folder 223)
  - United with Israel, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 224)
  - University Christian Movement, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 225)
  - Urban Improvement Corps, 1971-1972 (Box 28, Folder 226)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade [pamphlet], 1968 (Box 28, Folder 227)
  - Vietnam
    - Clippings and articles, 1965-1972 (Box 28, Folder 228 - 235)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1966 (Box 28, Folder 236)
  - Vietnam Commencement, 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 237)
  - Vietnam relief [funds for medical aid sent to Vietnam], 1966 (Box 29, Folder 238)
  - Vietnam Summer
    - General, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 239)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 240)
    - Project profiles, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 241)
    - Progress reports and "Worklists", 1967 (Box 29, Folder 242)
    - Publications, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 243 - 244)
    - Vietnam Summer News
      See: Oversize Folder 3
  - War Control Planners, Inc., 1965-1967 (Box 29, Folder 245)
  - War crimes, 1972, undated (Box 29, Folder 246)
  - War Resister's League, 1969-1970 (Box 29, Folder 247)
  - Waskow, Arthur I. ["Religious Upwelling on the Left"], Circa 1968 (Box 29, Folder 248)
  - Weddings, 1970-1971 (Box 29, Folder 249)
  - Welfare, 1972, undated (Box 29, Folder 250)
  - William Sloane Coffin Defense Fund, 1968-1969 (Box 29, Folder 251)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Circa 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 252)
  - Women's liberation, 1971, 1973 (Box 29, Folder 253)
  - World Assembly for Peace, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 254)
  - World Law Fund, 1972 (Box 29, Folder 255)
- Yale University Files, 1955-1977; Series III
  Yale University Files consist of materials specific to Coffin's position as Yale chaplain and as pastor of Church of Christ in Yale University. The series is arranged alphabetically. Materials related to his years as a student in Yale College and Yale Divinity School can be found in Series IV and Series V.